hi andrew
uh thanks for reaching out uh you uh
watched my my last discussion with john
and you commented uh some stuff about
buddhist symbolism especially and you
were also curious to learn more about
symbolism from the the catholic side so
uh of course i thought it would be nice
i saw it you also had several convex
exchanges with john with
chris as well and also on your channel
you have a bunch of other ones
so um yeah let's uh let's kick this off
yeah we've been we've been orbiting in
the same
circles and we have some of the same
concerns
um i i always enjoy listening to you
talk
because of the um
i guess i guess uh i guess because
you're a philosopher and you have a very
fine sense of of conceptual
understanding and
um but also you have i guess a spiritual
uh path
as well and you you you tend to bring
those together
in a way that interests me um i'm not
i'm not a pure philosopher i'm more of a
dabbler and
my background is is in literature
and music and yeah you seem to be able
to pick up patterns and to also ask
great questions uh for most of the the
videos i watched and but yes you were in
you were mostly
able to ask good questions i didn't know
exactly what even
you believed yourself but uh you were
always able to pinpoint
good questions to ask it to whomever you
were talking to
oh thank you very much i think i have
i'm better with the gestalt
than the details right so uh so
i i i i have a sort of gestalting mind
right
i have a sort of overview mind and
um i'm less good on the fine points
so i enjoy talking to people who are who
have a more refined intellect
than i do yeah yeah it's it also
okay sometimes i think i can sit in
conversations with uh
sometimes someone will take the role of
being sort of the the over mind of not
going too much into the details but
asking questions and then the other
person will sort of uh
try to think more short term but give
precise answers i get this feeling
sometimes for uh
even in the conversations i had with
john sometimes we sort of did
sometimes it went both ways like i think
our in our second conversation
i had like a i had a good grasp of
john's overall body of work and i asked
for such questions in a few places uh so
there i was more
trying to be all-encompassing and john
gave precise answers but for all of our
other discussions and especially the
last one i really felt it were
he he he sort of had a much
wider perspective and he was asking me
precise questions and i was able to
give precise answers that he found
interesting but i i was able to sort of
lose myself into the details and i could
trust that it would sort of
bring us back into like a wire topic
afterwards it was a
nice nice uh nice duel well on my
podcast what i've been
enjoying lately is just going deep with
people and i've also noticed that i've
enjoyed a a three-person dynamic a lot
and that i was i'm sort of like
i think of it as like a rock band where
i'm like the drummer or something or the
bassist or
you know and um i like this dynamic of
three because it's not just so
intense one-on-one and there there's
always someone to bring you back
kind of to uh um so i often my role in
the
discussions with guys like like john and
zach and sort of
um sort of they go very into the you
know intense
um conceptual stuff and i want to
compress that and i want to make that
particular that i want to make that
understandable to me and
so i sort of bring it back in every time
does that make
yes yeah i think so so yeah maybe we can
try to do this with uh
with symbolism to to start with um
so the way i see symbolism is
we're trying to use the same metaphors
and analogies to get that symbols
uh where we try to study let's see
structural relations between
the different layers of being to try to
pinpoint some
symbols where i see symbols at the
mediators between
those different layers of being so
one i like to use a lot is the the head
in the case of head body symbolism
because we're on the one end we are
material
uh our body is is is material
but we also have a mind and we know that
the
the head mediates between the two and we
don't have to get into the precise
um like theories of mind that
would you rather be a non-reductive
cyclist like john would you rather be a
dualist a materialist
it doesn't really matter as long as you
admit that there is something like mine
that there's something like matter
and we know that the head media is
between the two and we have
this uh this symbolic fact that
the head is a symbol that mediates
between our body
and our mind so we can see that the head
is a symbol of our
mind you can say right right and i
and we can use this
basic pattern and apply that other
levels of being as well the fact that
the hand mediates between the head and
the body is analogous to what happens
uh sorry the fact that the enemy is
between the mind and the body is
analogous what happens
in a cell between the the genetic
information
is mediated by the nucleus to the other
organelles so you have again something
material
different organelles in the cell that
are somehow related to information to
genetic
genetic information to the form of the
cell you can see the patterns that
actually hold
this all together and the the nucleus is
the symbol of the the cell it's the the
organelle that mediates between
the cell as a whole and the individual
organelles and we can
take this up at i o levels of being as
well right so that's what's happening
we don't really understand often how
how you know how we're using symbols all
the time when we talk about the atom
or something like that we're not
describing anything that's actual like
we're just
we're we're compressing a lot of
information and making a map and just
and calling that an atom but it doesn't
resemble
uh an atom in any kind of way right yeah
yeah you can
kill this don't we i mean yeah
yeah we have to guess i think that yeah
the atom can be an interesting one
it's it we do work with symbols
the the atom well the way we would
represent it let's say in a book
uh let's see you have the you have the
nucleus and then you have a few
particles orbiting around it like a
solar system
we know that it's not actually like this
but it's a good symbol
for the atom it's a good representation
to
communicate between us uh humans and
what actually happens within
a within a real atom so it mediates
between the atom and those
and in that sense it's it's a real
symbol and we
don't have the choice but to work with
with those all the time even with words
you can see words
this way you can say that symbols are a
mediator between
you know uh complexity
um and so it's a language that we can
understand that
it's always the mediator that makes the
information
complex information um
uh articulate to us or something
otherwise we would just
live in a sea of you know infinite sort
of
regress and chaos and and combinatorial
explosion
yeah john's language yeah we sort of be
stuck at the ground level of physics
it would just be like potential and
chaos and we need symbols to reach
higher yeah
we need symbols to abstract into higher
level phenomena
right higher level yeah so um yeah
um and we also need symbols to ground us
too like you talked about
higher level phenomena right yeah but i
would assume that we also need symbols
to bring us back into embodied reality
right at the same time so there's a sort
of um
you know upward motion and then a
grounding motion as well
yeah yeah yeah that's what symbols can
like allow
the ir to come down to our level if uh
let's say
yeah and we can probably get into what
would happen in buddhism for instance
but i know that within
let's say uh christianity when you go to
church
there are symbols that will make hit
between the community and you and
ultimately
we claim between uh the ground of being
and us and it will go through symbols
that we see in the church so
the fact that let's see we're all
assembled together in a building facing
the eucharist for instance uh is
the eucharist there will be a symbol of
the community and also of god uh that
unites all of us together
we all we're it's really like a body
united around itself it's
we're all facing in the same direction
we all bring our our own
like concerns and thoughts and so on to
this one point and we also let this one
point inform
all of us with all of its rich geology
and different people have different
let's say slivers of all of this in
their in their minds
but still we're all informed by this uh
one symbol that gathers all of us
uh and so this fact this symbol
will allow let's say transcendent value
ultimately i would claim the goal of
being if if and you know this is a
specifically christian claim but if you
think that
the ground of being really became
manifest in in judea 2000 years ago and
instituted
the eucharist then uh you can see that
through the ground of being
institute instituting this 2000 years
ago and us still doing it today
it's the part of being talking to us
through the symbol through the eucharist
and unfolding so his life 2000 years ago
through the eucharist through the church
in us as well today so
so as you said it's not only that when
you say ground of being that's a symbol
as well because there's no ground
right uh a literal ground there's no
bottom or
top right you just have to use that as
as a
short form right to to say that you're
within some kind of a cosmos yeah
yeah i think that's right it's it's the
because we do think that there
is a ground of being but obviously the
way we describe it is not perfect
because we're humans
so we use so we use
yeah we use metaphors or analogies i
guess metaphor is never perfect right
it's
it's it's always a short form of some
kind isn't it it's
because you're not you're not comparing
two equivalent things
yeah yeah it's difficult i've been
trying to articulate precisely what
could be the difference between
let's say mere symbol or let's say
mirror metaphor
and a symbol and i'm not exactly clear
how i would make the decision exactly
it's still it it all still seems i mean
it's difficult on one end because
different people have different ideas of
what a metaphor
is uh and i know that let's say symbols
can be wrong
you can get your symbolism wrong and
maybe
it can degenerate into something that's
not quite right but that
people could still call a metaphor i
don't know like um
i've been playing with especially
because are you talking about symbols
like
sacred symbols i think is what you're
talking about in some sense right
because there's just gimbals right
everything is a symbol a dog is a symbol
of a dog like the word dog
is a symbol of a dog it's just language
is symbolic
right but but when you're talking about
getting it right and wrong i think
you're talking
you're talking about symbol symbolism
within a sacred um
that's an interesting proposal i don't
think that is i think it can still be
wrong
even before we get to the level of a
a religion um and it also yeah even the
other way around because we do
claim within christianity there's
something real special even just about
language about logos
uh so even like even something as simple
as our symbolic participation in naming
the animals
still like sacred to some extent so
there would be a continuum
between everyday symbols of even just
language and
symbols that create the world like like
the eucharist or uh like like the
incarnation so
this so i would say it's more of a
continuum but you can get it wrong at
all of those different layers
if you think that uh let's see the
in a cell if you think that the
mitochondria is the head of the cell
then then you're getting it wrong
it's not like the inverted symbol or
something you might you can't get it
upside down
you might you might mistake the top the
top from the bottom and i think isn't
that what jonathan
talks a lot about is this inversion of
symbolism going on in our
world today yeah it can happen that it's
just just completely inverted
uh when you yeah you try to put the
bottom at the top sometimes it's just
also
like a mismatch of things um or
intuition starting out right but then
that finish up wrong
like i i've been playing with conspiracy
theories
and what conspiracy theories oh yeah
right
because you know when you see a
phenomenon that gathers a lot of
attention like
a conspiracy about 5g towers or about
vaccines or whatever
when it gathers a lot of attention it's
typically because there is
there is some intuition there that is
widespread enough that it's
there's likely some truth to it but then
it goes up in some direction
uh so i've used cell towers
uh in the past because they're
conspiracy right now people burning down
some towers because they think that
5g technology has either caused or is
helping fuel the
the kobe epidemic in some way and
this starts with a good intuition of
people in tweeting that some towers have
a cause a role to play
in the crisis somehow that
and and that's true because our our
ability to communicate
with uh with cell phones and with social
media so has has helped fuel
a panic there and it has made the crisis
worse we can
go into other causal factors but the
basic idea that there are causal
patterns that exist at the social level
uh that are mediated by cell phone
towers is true so
it's true that cell phone towers mediate
between a social phenomena
and our own material uh vibes
it's a true that's in that sense cell
towers are a symbol for the
for for the virus but you even if you
get like this basic
intuition right it doesn't get that you
doesn't mean that you'll get the
symbolism quite right because those
those people who then go on to claim
that uh
the the towers are materially
responsible for the virus at this point
they they start to mess up their their
symbolism they think that the way that
cell towers mediate between the virus
and us
is through like some some mysterious uh
technology in the web themselves
yeah so that's mistaking uh that's a
levels of symbolism like you're
you see the whole world as this material
substance
but you're not seeing the subtle root of
that
yeah um i think that that's what i'm
hearing you're saying are people are not
understanding that
um or rather perhaps they're being
they're being governed by
symbols unconsciously right
they're being controlled by archetypes
and symbols and all kinds of things
that they don't really understand
because they're only interpreting
reality
in the first degree does that make sense
yeah yeah yeah let's see what you mean
there
and at this point maybe i could say that
i don't know if it would degenerate in
metaphor already but there are other
instances of conspiracy theories like
people
who blame bill gates for putting uh
microchips and vaccines to uh
to somehow track us and
like this is another instance where the
the there's a basic
intuition there of you know bill gates
being responsible for laptops and
uh a bunch of technology that we
actually use and that can actually be
used to track us
but it's something we do voluntarily
it's not something that gets those
through
through vaccines but the basic intuition
that uh bill gates is behind technology
that uh
has allowed us to make ourselves
trackable really this is a real
like social little pattern but yeah
excuse me i'm just closing the window
here because i have some
construction outside yeah sure
yeah but because people then cast it
down try to cast it on to the material
level
uh they somehow somewhere comes up with
the idea that
vaccines mediate between bill gates and
us and
this is wrong uh this is wrong symbolism
because it's not true that the vaccine
is a mediator between
like technology and between bill gates's
technology and ourselves
but maybe in that sense it's still a
metaphor where
they they see a like there's a loose
connection between
like technology getting into our bodies
through vaccines and
uh it gets tracking us uh somehow but
it becomes loose at this point i can
still see like that there's basically
clearing of intuition there
but uh maybe so maybe at the same also
dangerous and powerful because
uh because symbols are powerful right
they they change our minds and they
they uh you know cause us to behave in
certain ways and
and uh so so if if we don't understand
them
if we don't understand what's really if
we don't study them deeply
then we can easily get lost in in in
this
you know unconscious symbolism i think
yeah yeah yeah
and something that i think honey talks
about
i'm reading him at the moment too
actually i've been talking a lot about
him and thinking a lot about him
yeah cool yeah if we like we if you'd
like we can try to
piss out some something about symbolism
from him because
i i talked to i talked with
craig stewart i don't know if you have
ever watched some of his videos he has
talked with jonathan and with
paul mcclay he has done
uh he has been studying gerard for for
several years
and he pointed out to me lately that
the you can see jihad as
i think maybe a richer symbolic system
it doesn't like come out and
talk about it as his symbolic system but
instead of talking right the is the
central idea his central idea is is the
scapegoat
um and and i guess the scapegoat is a
symbol isn't it it's a symbol it's a
symbol of what's wrong and you you
you you prop up a scapegoat and then you
destroy it to create this
um you know to create this artificial
peace in the society
um so that sort of you know there's not
this war at all against all
and then we keep looking for scapegoats
unconsciously we keep looking for
symbols of what's wrong
right um of what's you know sick in our
society i
i have a friend who thinks that you know
that idea is the most
important idea you know there is right
now it's absolutely so
because it's it's really it's really the
root of
of all conflict on some some level is
the scapegoat mechanism
yeah i think it's one part of the symbol
um
i think gerard tries to point to
something like even more fundamental and
the skateboarding mechanism would be a
consequence of it but his main thing is
[Music]
is imitation the so instead of talking
about let's say head and body or
center and periphery he talks about it
in terms of
the model and the imitator yeah the
model
right yeah so and it's
it's cool in in uh his book uh thinks
that instance from the foundations of
the world
he he says that you know
you can see it in aristotle and plato
that they add
some they actually add metaphysics of
imitation
because in plato for instance you have
the whole idea that there's
like god or the form of forms from which
gemini forms
and uh like you always have survey
likeness between forms that
trickles down to the material world
ultimately but it's always of the
limitation of forms that are that are
ira um and apparently plato had some
made some weird comments about let's see
the arts and he tried to steer people
away from imitation because he could
sense that there was something
like dangerous about the imitation yeah
and yeah he he he was plato
i think i was reading that too and he he
was saying that you know he was trying
he really wanted to censor the arts
actually
because he thought he thought it was it
was it was very very dangerous
um yeah
because of i guess this memetic quality
is it you know
if you have a model then people imitate
that model and
yeah it's like you could sense that
things could get out of control
and yeah where is he trying to control
it too much right so so that would be
like
that would be like a mania for control
yeah and gerald tried to
worry where he went further than
aristotle or plato is that he
explained that it's not just that we
let's say imitate what other people's
what other people do or like it's not
just that forms emitted what the other
forms do about but
once you reach the human level it's
strange in that
we don't just imitate the behaviors of
people we make it also their desires
and uh so for instance in in monkeys you
can see that
people will imitate whatever other
monkeys do like the
the the chief monkey if the chief monkey
does something then the other monkeys
will will
tend to copy him but not when it's like
about consuming some
something not when it's about a desire
like if the the chief monkey like grabs
a woman or uh
another one grabs another monkey uh or
uh if
you grab some food something this is not
something that the lower monkeys will
imitate
because they don't like imitate desires
but something that we humans do if
someone wants something we tend to
imitate that person as well right if if
uh
the object of our desire becomes
exponentially more attractive if
somebody else also desires
that woman or iphone or you know
whatever it is uh it's it's it's also
the secret of advertising it's like
it's like it's um imitating
uh you know we imitate we want what
other people want and then there's a c
he talks about envy gerard doesn't he
and then yeah the envy is this this
very hidden emotion that we don't admit
to ourselves you know
it's all about wanting what our neighbor
wants
yeah yeah and there used to be a
distinction between envy and jealousy
like jealousy was when you when you want
something
because someone else has it but nv goes
further in that
it's not only that you want something
because someone else has it but that if
you can't have it you would rather the
thing be destroyed so that the other
person doesn't have it as well like it
goes
goes a bit further and i think it's a
yeah it's a powerful emotion that we
don't
recognize maybe enough uh today but
yeah and and then jihad used this
symbolism of okay so so people uh
desire things through mediators we
desire things through models
that's why you talked about the triangle
so we desire something through our model
so we deserve
something via a model we imitate other
people's desires so
yeah and so this will have the
consequence of mimetic rivalry where
people will
will all start to desire the same things
and you will there will be tons of
conflict
uh so you can't get so one
one consequence of jihad's symbolism is
that okay there will be
like wars of or there will be conflict
and the other thing you can predict is
that once people start crawling in
piling up against a scapegoat then
people will also emit that desire
to escape called the victim so that will
so so there's
so the the two mechanisms that explain
why people like fragment and then why
people gather again
uh against the scapegoat or explain
within uh
shiraz uh imitator and model
model and imitator symbolism yeah and
yeah i'll have to play more about it
though cause it's uh it seems almost too
good to be true
if if you read he seems to be able to
explain so much stuff we did that it's
it's a bit surprising like it's yeah it
just sounds too good to be true
yeah well it um i mean if you talk about
christ
as being the ultimate scapegoat
mechanism or the ultimate
you know revelation of the scapegoat
yeah um it makes sense uh
um the power of christianity makes a lot
more sense to me
you know as somebody who's never you
know been a christian uh you know
gerard helped me really understand
christianity i think
yeah otherwise i might not have
understood it um
because i because i very early we
started working with buddhism and
buddhism i think um
if you're if you're a western person uh
growing up in in you know in a christian
world and you see all the
let's say decadence of the christian or
or or
if you see you see a lot of dead
christianity let's say yeah
i don't know if you would agree with me
but yeah yeah i'm not living not living
christianity
yeah so that was the christianity that i
was exposed to so i went to
to study buddhism because buddhism you
you would actually there was actually
practices you could you know
he could do yeah other than you know uh
let's say dogma that you were supposed
to
um you know you were supposed to to
imitate or
you're supposed to you're supposed to
imitate all these series of dogmas
it didn't make sense to me um as a young
person
where sitting sitting on a meditation
cushion for hours and hours
you know trying to understand my you
know what your my mind
and the body and the world that was much
more direct for me
but then later on i i i sort of
came back to wanting to understand
christianity through
you know through probably people like
gerard and carl ewing and
other people who are not necessarily
central within the church
um northrop's right and people like that
may
made me interested in christianity
uh again so yeah yeah that makes sense
and something i've been exploring lately
the idea of how it is that
christianity itself grows through deaths
and rivers so
it uh like in our case in the west
christianity has
has faded into uh atheism
really yeah but and
it's not the first time that
christianity fades and then rises again
there's starting with christ and then
the apostles
uh once yeah i i i won't go through all
of it because i know you listen to my
conversation with jonathan you have this
basic idea of like christ dies and the
apostles
become him and then the apostle dies the
apostles die and then
like the different churches are founded
and the churches themselves die and then
they take over uh uh empires so it like
keeps growing this way and there's
some some you can get maybe at least
some some hope that it's also what's
occurring right now with
jira i've heard i don't know if it ever
himself say this but ever people say
that
one of the one of the things that
security has made possible is for us to
see how special
christianity is compared to other
religions but once we
we get away from christianity and we try
to look at it compared to other
religious systems we see how weird it is
once we can compare it with other myths
we can see how it inverts the
scapegoating
mechanism and that this is something
very surprising and that
once you know it it can explain a lot of
things so general has written a lot
to explain all of that stuff um
and what i wonder like i wonder within
other religions you know again
buddhism is what i'm most familiar with
because i've been
practicing it since my 20s and i've
practiced in different traditions
um i i wonder i i wonder
um you know um
i wonder where the scapegoat mechanism
fits in into buddhism
um i wonder if i wonder i wonder if if
there's i wonder you know i just i
wonder about that yeah
yeah i was curious to ask to you about
this as well because i think i i've just
i know that i know that in buddhism for
example there's different schools of
buddhism right
yeah there's um there's um the older
schools which are called indiana and
they're based in
sutra and they're based in renunciation
and there's this
there's this false idea that people have
the buddhism is about emptiness right
that that's the whole story of buddhism
it's about
becoming void or empty or becoming
nothing and that sort of thing um
and then there's the mahayana school
which which which is sort of like
um the indiana school is about
discipline
um and practice and self-realization you
could say
uh but but that that was recognized to
be a limited
uh perspective self-realization and so
the next stage of buddhism
was mahayana buddhism which means great
vehicle
so narrow vehicle would be like you you
work on yourself you discipline yourself
for the next vehicle would be called
great vehicle
um and that would be that would be your
developed compassion and wisdom
and then there was this notion of the
bodhisattva who is sort of like the
savior
i guess he goes and he goes and um he
gives up nirvana he
he sacrifices you could say nirvana um
to to help beings so there's this very
big altruistic
uh quality to that and also
philosophical quality to that
i mean the highest philosophy you can
get is in the mahayana it goes up to the
mariana
and then the next part is called the
next tradition the tradition you find in
northern
you know in tibet and in
actually there was but there was there
was tantric buddhism all over uh
of the world at one point and was
completely destroyed by islamic fake
invasions
all over the east i should say not the
world um
but but but it but it sort of
crystallized in tibet
and and it has its origins in india and
that would that's a tradition
um which that's the tradition that
interests me which
which kind of it goes it goes it goes
one step further than uh into
let's say uh deeper into symbolism the
necessary
it's it's more um
um rather than the
it moves beyond the propositional uh
into the symbolic
you know because you could say and you
work more with symbols and you work more
with the
you know with with the body and it's
more you work more with um
you know it's it's i had this discussion
with john about that and i haven't
really finished my discussion with him
about it because
he goes into transrational you could say
so it has
aspects that you know i was listening to
somebody say i think it was cs lewis
that christianity has this
connection to paganism right that um
that makes it
um like that makes it
universal um you know so you have you
can in christianity you you can you can
have
high high-end philosophy but you can
also reach common people
and because because there's this whole
um
you have the rituals which you know you
eat the you know the body and the blood
of christ and
that kind of thing very primordial but i
think that vajrayana has
a bit of a quality of of that and so
when i look back at christianity i see
aspects of christianity that remind me
in some sense
of of adriana um even the trinity is
there like that
and they talk about the three bodies of
the buddha
there's dharmakayas and bogota in your
monaco and the
subtle causal non-dual or
um or you could say that dermatochais
i've heard of
tibetan master says is love right the
physical body is is love right
it's manifest as love which reminds me
of of christianity
in some way so um interesting
so i i i um and so i think it goes a
little bit
further than what you normally normally
people think of buddhism
they associate it with emptiness uh but
actually
a higher view is is emptiness and love
and luminosity or
to get those two things together yeah
that's interesting because do you have
an idea where this emptiness caricature
came about and why it became so
prevalent
uh well i think that um
uh i mean i don't i don't i wouldn't i
wouldn't know how to analyze that
historically um uh because
no nothing is no thingness right so
so so uh but that gets that that seems
like a nihilism
on some level um but who was it this
this guy that john was talking about
um this this eastern philosopher you're
saying one of the reasons that nihilism
has never been a problem in the east
is because we have this notion they have
this notion of they have a positive
notion of
of no thingness or shinyata or emptiness
there's a positive
notion of nothingness it's not a
negative it's not a nihilism it's not a
you know it's not just that you know
where you you um
it's not a sort of suicide like when i
hear gerard talk about buddhism
he always talks about it in terms of
it's some kind of
nihilism but i think that's i think he's
he's he's using he's
it's a western filter on on yeah on what
buddhism is and i think a lot of the
the west people think of buddhism really
in terms of a lot of western concepts
because
they're in the west they don't have
people what does
buddhists often don't understand western
buddhists
don't understand that they're being
christians or stoics or
epicureans when they're when they're
trying to analyze
they know as buddhism and you don't know
this whole other richer side of buddhism
which is very um i don't know it's much
more
um it has more of the emotionalism that
you have in christianity
you're gonna love and compact love it
love and worship is more important
whereas you know in the west uh in the
west people tend to think of buddhism as
sort of this
sterile kind of uh you know like this
kind of rational religion
which uh you know i i
i've had i i i don't know if i've got to
the bottom of this with john in my
discussions with him but
you know because i'm a practicing
buddhism and he he talks about the
religion that's there's no religion so
yeah at one point and i said okay you
know there i'm gonna just say okay i'm a
buddhist okay because i'm gonna commit
to that particular
path um where john practices a lot of
buddhism
things but he won't commit to that he'll
sort of
he'll he'll do neoplatonism and and
and practice buddhist techniques and
yeah yeah yeah i wanted to ask you about
jihad
because i've heard him yeah from what i
heard him
talk about buddhism it was excited as a
way to
try to dampen let's say the skeptic
mechanism by
renunciating desire yeah that's the
thing
sutriana buddhism is about renunciation
that's true
but there's also uh the next part of the
contract buddhism is
is not about renunciation it's it's
actually it's actually
very it's about it's it's very um
uh embodied yeah so he's he's
interpreting uh
one half of buddhism he's saying one
half of buddhism but not the other
other half of buddhism yeah and he's
right
yeah and i mean there's a pronunciation
aspect of christianity too isn't there
and then there's a
then there's the you know where you know
um i think in tantriana you don't
renounce
um because at the like the
the art of the the christ's response to
this computing mechanism is that
okay so instead of us always trying to
like imitate one another and you sort of
get
this mess of different people trying to
imitate different people but also
wanting to somehow differentiate
themselves from from the other so you
get this
just mess of at the human level of
different people with
different desires and copying each
other's
it's just a wholeness and the solution
will be to
imitate instead of christ just tries to
imitate the father just tries to muddle
his desires after the
desires of the of the grand being of the
desert father and then if
we we do this like christ then on the
one hand we risk being scapegoats as
well
like like he was but we won't
participate in
the scapegoating mechanism just just
like he didn't participate
in it so i guess is is this
that that seems very tender to me you
take a desire and you transform it
rather than you repress it or push it
away or or
or hide from it or yeah you would rather
try to
sort of model the desires of the buddha
i guess
well um
it's complicated because uh
i think the buddha is not a model i
think you go beyond the buddha being a
model
i think i think maybe that's where and
you go beyond
because perhaps that's the difference
between christianity and christianity
christ is the ultimate
model in buddhism there is no ultimate
model perhaps
but but you do they have something
called skillful means and that's called
which means you know you practice
devotional practices
until you go beyond them okay
that makes any sense okay so but where
do you get to the point where you don't
just
model your desires after other people's
desires
when you don't just model your desires
after
um probably i guess it's it's it's sort
of like
you have you you assimilate um
uh you know you work with the models
or the master of the teacher or
in buddhism that the living buddha is
more important than the historical
buddha
you know for example yeah so so the so
so
we don't even care about we care there's
devotion towards the historical buddha
but but it's not it's it's not for me i
don't think it's the ultimate
ultimate thing because everything has
but in nature
so uh so um so actually
the living buddha is the the teacher
that you work with is
means more it would be like saying that
the pope means more than
christ or something you know or
something like that the
pope was more valuable than christ
because he's the living embodiment he's
here right right right now
yeah yes um and the pope is not a symbol
for for god
the pope is is god not god because
because it's not theistic it's not a
create creator
but uh i guess you you would still say
that not like the ground of being
yeah yeah yeah yeah you would still say
that the buddha is a symbol for the
ground being
in that immediate between the ground of
being and the buddha is a symbol for the
grounded being but a symbol is not an
ultimate
expression it's not a you know um
yeah i don't know it's something i've
been playing with like if you take
symbols
seriously as i said mediators are real
things like
they exist like my head exists and like
the nucleus in a cell exists
if there are real things uh
i don't know if we do we think
christianity
we do say that this christ is the
perfect image of the father we do say
that uh
he also like is the word of the father
so i think you you could say that
i don't think it's too far from saying
from the way i've been talking about
symbols as mediators
um i don't think it would be
wrong to say that christ is a symbol of
the father
the way that is the image of the father
and is also the word spoken by the
father
but like the difference and people will
emphasize this when they talk about
about christ in terms of of the word in
terms of the logos
whereas our word is distinct from us
because we can't express ourselves
perfectly
god the ground of being can express
himself perfectly so his word
is not like separate from him it is like
a perfect knowledge of himself it is a
perfect expression of him
so in that sense like the the perfect
image of the father is christ is also
is also like equal with the father and
same thing
uh i think you would say with uh like
the
the image in that that way something you
will see with a symbol
like christ is the perfect symbol of the
father and whereas our earthly symbols
are separate from the things they
symbolize it wouldn't be the case
in thank you yeah so the so it's
actually it's beyond the symbol in some
sense
yeah um even though it's it's a symbol
that's beyond the symbol because it's
perfectly unified
yeah it's like perfect for real with the
real yeah yeah
yeah yeah and i i don't think it would
be too distinct from what happens within
buddhism where
like the let's say the buddha or the
teacher
well i guess you wouldn't probably see
that he's a perfect symbol but at least
it is it's supposed to bring you really
close to the ground of being
mm-hmm yeah well i i think uh what what
do you mean by perfect is it
you know what does perfect mean if you
mean that he becomes sort of
it's like yeah well i guess christ is
the god man he's the perfect
perfect man that's that's the symbol of
christ in some sense
[Music]
um but it's interesting that that that
symbol that that perfect man gets
crucified
that's interesting to me yeah it's
almost saying that
um that perfection is not
is not possible in this world or
something something anyway i'm not i'm
not a christian so
i'm just riffing here maybe yeah i think
i think it's sort of almost the other
way around where
the there's the idea that like christ's
sacrif
christ obedience and to death was
perfect or another
to put it is that there's no
yeah no man has greater love than this
then to lay down his life for his
friends there's this idea and i've heard
it
that
god created man so that
he could save him uh like
because it's a way to show show his
glory okay so
god could have just created nothing the
ground being could have just created
nothing and
it's still like god would still have all
the classical attributes it would still
have been all powerful or good and so on
just that you wouldn't have deployed
this uh this goodness and uh and so on
then you know he created angels and then
it's a way to we say that it's still a
way to
for him to show his glory to create
things like it shows his omnipotent and
so on
to create principalities and powers you
would say in more secular terms
uh but then you can't like love angels
in the same way that you can love humans
you can't forgive angels like there's a
this idea that the
the forms like the patterns the the the
angels are basically
higher level patterns but once you
create them they're because they're eye
level patterns their forms they're
they're stuck they either fall or they
they they stay out so so that's it you
can't really forgive them
but with humans our our wills allow us
to
to fall and then to ask forgiveness oh
that's interesting i can find an analogy
to buddhism there too um because
then there's this wheel right then all
the realms are in a kind of wheel you
have the human realm
and you have the god realm you know uh
and you have the heaven realm and you
have the the realm of the the
the jealous gods and then you have the i
don't know if i'm getting it right here
you have the animal realm and you have
the hell room and there's this kind of a
wheel right
yeah hungry ghosts you know at the end
what
the realm of the hungry ghosts huh
interesting and the hungry ghosts are
are people who are just
they you know they're just become you
know
addicted to facebook or they spend all
their lives on instagram
[Music]
actually they have very thin necks and
big bellies so they
they try to consume things and they they
can't digest them
they're just off consuming and because
you know so it's a very it's a very
apropos uh realm for for today and in
the internet and
the zombie apocalypse and all that but
but anyway
there's these realms and the realm that
you can you can be liberated in is the
human realm
you know the human realm is a realm of
desire
yeah oh yeah yeah yeah because
so that's so that's there's so so that
you can't be
if you're in the god realm you can't be
liberated and eventually you fall down
into the hell room
you know even if you live in this glory
for thousands of years
in in great palaces you're eventually
going to end up
you know in in in the animal realm in
the hell realm
and uh that's gonna be very hard because
you've been gone
yeah yeah yeah but but the human realm
is is a unique realm because it's the
realm where we can become
uh liberated of samsara or
from okay yeah
yeah but that reminds me of when you
were saying that that you know that that
in christianity the person you can love
is is human
right um you can't love the angels you
can't love the well i mean you can but
it's not in the same way like you can't
express the same level of love because
you can't
forgive a an angel or you can't forgive
god
either because they like they they're
what's the word they're simple like they
don't they don't change they're
unchanging
so yeah they can't like try to repent
and ask forgiveness one but humans can
so there's the idea that god created
man so that man would have like changing
uh
desires and so on and that man would
likely fall it would have been nice if
we didn't but it was quite likely that
we did
and then god could manifest like his
infinite love by for saving us and
forgiving us
so like the because we started talking
about this because you mentioned the
idea that it was weird for
christ being perfect that he would be be
crucified like
like perfection wouldn't be possible in
our world but
it's it's christianity tries to even
flip this to say that the the most
beautiful this is the rest of the
direction
right because yes yeah it does
like the idea that even
it's one of the reasons why the the
christian story as
has been doing so well in spite of
everything and
the fact that it is paul sometimes
mentions the story i find it really cool
the missionaries would go let's see in
the in the jungle somewhere in the
in asia and they would go live with
a tribe there learn learn the language
like create an alphabet for them
then translate the bible for them in
that alphabet and then
try to evangelize them and so on and
while the missionaries was were there
like they wouldn't really get anywhere
it wouldn't work but at some point the
missionaries would just sort of pack up
and leave
uh but then if you came back like a few
decades later
like that tribe would have taken the
book and would have sort of
let emerge their own version of
christianity from the story
and i think it goes to the fact that but
if you
if you take the story just seriously
enough to let it touch you
it's it's crazy to think of god
becoming a man to save humanity and to
to go through all of this torture and
makes the so it's sort of a flip saying
perfection
we have to start seeing like that this
like doing what
christ did on the cross was actually
perfect and it's an unviable thing to do
like
it's a it's a good thing to have done
and we should all just
aspire to it and it's why so many of the
early christians were martyred like
why they did precisely follow in those
footsteps and were martyred most of them
yeah gerard distinguishes between the
sacrificial aspect of christianity
uh which which he thinks is really
really rooted to this old religion of
paganism
and then um and then the christianity
understands the
uh lie scapegoat and you know he says
jesus it was
murdered you know as a common criminal
it's like
this is this this this means that this
means that the scapegoat mechanism has
been revealed as
being being a kind of kind of alive
right yeah yeah yeah and i wonder i was
scared to know within buddhism if
there's an equivalent or
i don't even know much about like the
cultures of sacrifice that occurred
within asia i know that
makes the claim that you know we can't
find this pretty much anywhere but
well i can talk i know in the bond
culture in tibet there was actually
human sacrifice and
all kinds of uh things like that um
and uh you know and buddhism
there is you won't find
um you won't find you find symbolic
sacrifice in buddhism but you will never
find
human sacrifice or animals certainly not
animal sacrifice
and buddhism wouldn't sacrifice an
animal um
that would be just the worst thing in
the world right so i they must have had
a way to deal with the scapegoat
mechanism
in some in some sense they must have you
know because they integrated in tibetan
buddhism they integrated
some of the shamanistic bond tradition
and then the thing called tibetan
buddhism came about
um in tibetan buddhism you know
there it would be unthinkable to
actually
sacrifice a you know an animal or a
person or anything anything like that
i think at some point in tibet there are
no even
it's not a perfect culture so i don't
want to romanticize it
people in america romanticize tibetan
culture because it was in many ways
medieval but i think the way that you
transcend the scapegoat mechanism is
through
what's called sadness practice
so you make an offering of your life
energy in some sense
without killing something yeah yeah but
does that make any any
sense yeah i think so because you can
see this happening within christianity
as well where
the same way that okay instead of just
trying to model his desires after what
people were doing around him christ
did model his desires after something
higher uh
instead of talking about the father
within buddhism i guess you could say he
tried to model his desires after being
after the grand being and then in doing
doing that was actually a form of
self-sacrifice so instead of
scapegoating others like everyone else
does
christ like scapegoated himself or let
himself be escaped
so he offered like part of himself
instead of sir
instead of skip voting others and then
what we should do is the same thing as
he did so
we should parts of ourselves
rather than sacrificing let's say goats
or participating in the
sacrifice of other other others but in
uh you know in some way
there's a lot of imagery of sacrifice
and dead tantric buddhism
it's interesting uh um i know i know
somebody who they went to see a cuban
uh you know a cuban let's say um voodoo
practitioner or whatever shaman of some
kind
and um and they wanted him to sacrifice
a goat
or something like this uh and he refused
and
and uh he changed it so they sacrificed
you know they offered a banana and some
rum instead
yeah you know because because it was
transforming that that kind of
notion of sacrifice um into uh
um into something not non-violent and uh
so there is images in the east you know
of if you look at the image of cali do
you know kali
kali is is the hindu hindu goddess and
he has a he has a necklace full of
skulls and he's trampling
corpse and he has weapons and he has
there's a lot there's
there's it seems very pagan um um
there's image there's images of of using
that energy
you know to transform yeah um
transform that you know um as a
transformative
um mechanism yeah yeah just be yeah then
i'll
add figures if you know like how this
shift from concrete
actual sacrifices in tibet to the point
where now it has become something
symbolic and more like the sort of
self-sacrifice that
has happened within christianity where
you know in
gerar's claim is that well this happened
in the west because of
christ's influence uh you reveal the
mechanism and show this a way out of it
by
self-sacrifice rather than other
sacrifice
and i'd be curious if you know the
history within
uh buddhism that also went away from
this kind of
well i mean the history of you know the
buddha
um for example um
he he was it was a it was a rebellion
against the caste system
in india and it's that sort of
primitivism
and um so um
so you can read the the early text of
the buddha and the polycon and it's like
libraries full of stuff and it's it's
very um
um progressive you could say compared to
you know how
you know it's very uh progressive is the
wrong word because
that's become such an ugly ugly word
it's almost like
perhaps it's similar to neoplatonism or
plato in aristotle or if it's praying
it's very
um you know it's very rational it's very
oh yes so i don't know if i'm answering
your question exactly but
but there's been some stepping out of
the
let's say roman circus or the caste
system
or or the the worldly
principalities uh going off into and
going off and
and starting the sangha which is the
community
yeah and uh so perhaps there's another
analogy to
the christian story in that sense you
know
the desert fathers went out into the
desert and left rome behind
yeah just as yeah it's
it's it's less brutal let's see rather
than you know
christ being only
having a public ministry for three years
until it was crucified and then
so this setting the physical example for
people to follow
for the buddha i guess it was more uh it
was more of a common sense thing today
that we would say okay so he
found something true and then he sort of
explained it to people and then this
just grew
rather than being crucified after three
years of teaching this
yeah yeah yeah i mean you can you can
find some pretty wild stories about
about his life um
so i wouldn't want to cast it in this
like
a rational sense you know yeah i
wouldn't want to cast it in
um but on the other hand there's there's
in in the mythology in the mytho poetics
there's lots of different buddhas
there's not just
many buddhists right buddhas are sort of
like there's been there's they're
they're they're future buddhas there's
past buddhists there's
you know uh in tibet in tibet actually
the
the tantric buddha is is worshipped more
than shakira's he's more
and he's more uh important than chucky
that's interesting yeah i'd like to jump
back to
something we talked about earlier
because yeah it
seems like you had your thoughts on on
the other thing when you said you know
in
your early 20s when you didn't think
that christianity made much much sense
since it was just too prepositional
whereas you could go to
like practice buddhism and
be involved in it bodily with your
senses and so on
so yeah well you know i i went to
practice zen
and you would sit and meditate for hours
and end right and that would have a
certain kind of effect so you go
directly into spiritual practice
whereas if you go to church you're
supposed to believe all these things and
you know it's like but just that was for
me as being a you know russian investor
i don't need to
be dismissive of the tradition in any
way i know there's living
you know there's living i know there's
living in dead traditions of
buddhism there's a lot of you know token
buddhism
as well or or you know wrong-headed
as well but my impression of
christianity was uh
was i i didn't feel that the people i
met in christian world and
were worthy of emulation or um
because i didn't meet those people i
know they're there but i i didn't meet
those people if i didn't meet jonathan
and you and you know i didn't mean
intelligent christians i
i would go to sunday school and they'd
tell me to draw some pictures and gave
me some
yeah crazy stories and i didn't
understand
you know you know so so i i i didn't
have
i didn't make that connection to
christianity until i i didn't make a
connection
to christianity until i'd gone through
buddhism and then i could understand
christianity which is interesting i
don't
i'm not saying i understand christianity
but i could have some
affinity for for for christianity and
christian stories and
yeah yeah yeah yes make sense to you
yeah yeah that makes a lot of sense um
because also with
you know i i reverted after i reverted
to christianity just in the last few
years after
like doing philosophy and listening and
talking to jonathan and so on so it
became
more viable as time went on and it's
yeah it's a so
strange and sad shouldn't say strange
necessarily but it's a sad story that
each time christianity has to die before
it reborns that each time you know
that that death is tragic and it's
saddened it's
not it's bad for a lot of people
initially it started with christ
and then all these apostles suffered and
like all the early churches suffered and
so it just like
keeps escalating levels as the church
grows but
what i find interesting in your story is
that you you could
you could feel that it wasn't working
right
um and now
in the just in the last few years then
you can
on the one it's because of what you
learned in buddhism but also because of
the
like the christian figures that are
emerging on this in this corner of the
internet particularly that
come up with something that is more
attractive to people
yeah so yeah if you have any
idea of what's going to happen next it
would be yeah i'd be interested
what's going to happen next well i think
that
there's going to be a revival of all the
religions next i think they're all going
to be
reborn and come into though you know
chris
you know but as just as buddhism was to
the west
christianity moves to the east you know
um
i have a friend alexander i talk to a
lot who's a
zoroastrian and i think zoroastrianism
is growing for god's sake
so so so so because i think that you
know the the
the society without that is
unsustainable
and uh and shallow and consumeristic and
you know the result is the zombie
apocalypse so people need to find
um you know a spiritual
dimension to their lives in one way or
another
yeah um so so i think
i think uh i think i al the other thing
is that i i don't know what you think
about this but
i think that religions change don't they
i mean over time they don't just remain
like the traditionalists would you know
see okay
how people practice christianity in the
medieval
times would have to be it would have to
be different now i mean i i think that
buddhism would have to be different in
in uh you know
i live in france and with america than
it was in china or japan
and i think christianity will have to
um uh become
something else and it probably is become
something else before it can be reborn
because
if it remains a shallow dogma or this
kind of triumphalism of
uh you know where you just believe in
something
and and you know people are too
intelligent
for that and i know there is a more
kind of christianity than the kind that
that you know
the fundamentalist people are selling
yeah i think it's a we can understand it
with
like the symbolism of peter and john or
the symbolism of the
okay so there's a hidden part of
all those traditions that's not gonna
change like um
in the same way you can even take a
person like there's a part of me
that doesn't change that never changes
like i can always tell that
i can take gp 20 years ago who has like
no no the same atoms like all of the
particles are different like physically
it's all different
but it's still there's a something
hidden something more abstract
that was there 20 years ago that is
still here now
uh and i think it's going to be the same
thing with
those different traditions like there's
gonna be something in them there's a an
abstract
uh link that has never been lost so like
christianity 2000 years ago is
still like the same christianity that is
at the hidden level but at the manifest
level it's always different
like even my body at the manifest level
is always different every microsecond
i'm manifesting myself at different
in different ways that's a very good
point yeah and within christianity we
like we have great symbolism for this i
think it's i i find it crazy that no
one's talking about this
uh so i've been like arping are thinking
about it recently but
there's the symbols of peter and john
where
there are a lot of stories i mentioned
just two when i talked with
with john last time but there
the idea is that it's very clear if you
read uh john's gospel
especially towards the end you have john
who represents the
the hidden part of the church
and there are a few illustrations for
this like he lays on the breast of
christ at
the supper also the fact that i think
that's that's very interesting and i i
sort of blew my mind when my friend
jacob russell told me this
if you read john's gospel
john is never named he's always just
described as
the the apostle whom jesus loved so it's
sort of hidden
it is not it's not there and for peter
who represents the the concrete like the
the everyday
the manifestation of the church uh he
on the one end you can say you can tell
that peter is sort of a
it's it's not very reflective let's see
like he
he he tends to act really quickly and he
gets corrected by christ
or by others he's just when uh at some
point they're they're they're in a ship
uh once uh jesus as sort of a as
resurrected
um john of course was the the hidden the
center
can see that christ is on the shore uh
through waiting for them so as soon as
peter
hears this he's just like i think he's
naked on the boat because people use the
fish naked apparently but it's a good
symbol for
like being naked in the garden and and
he sort of just puts on some clothes and
then like
runs runs through christ but you can
just swim in the water like this
it just gets like pacified by the other
apostles anyways
and then in opposition to john being
hidden and not being named in his gospel
peter is named all the time and christ
says that
peter is the name he used to be used to
be called
simon but his name peter when christ
makes him his rock the stone upon which
is going to found the church and
in in several languages you can see this
in the name so in in french
uh peter is
it's the word for stone so okay right
yeah so peter becomes like the the
manifestation the concrete like
the stuff you can see like the the stone
that marks
the the the area right the salinity or
the uh
of the of the church right and then i
should say that this is
it's not it's like the the the explicit
solidity
not the identity yeah
because peter will actually go on to die
and you can read this at the end of the
of his gospel where christ tells peter
that peter is going to be martyred
and you have this idea that the concrete
manifestation has to die like that's how
christianity will expand whereas the
center john will not die
crisis that jungle theory until uh until
peter comes back
and in the church you all what you've
seen is always a
sort of a an expression starting from
the center
that goes to the outside and dies and
then each time
like it makes more ground for the center
to expand next time
and there was this great mysterious
relationship between the center
and and the periphery and this with our
church lots of cool examples where
for instance you had um several councils
where
a bunch of priests and bishops would
gather for for months to draft let's say
a certain a certain trade or something
to condemn some samaritans
and after all of these people in
explicit powers an explicit authority
would
have spent all of this time doing this
they would go see a site somewhere
uh who has no authority and has been
doing weird things like there was an
uh ethic in one of the early councils
they went to see
uh a man named saint simeon who spent
years living on it i think it spent like
decades it's really living
sort of on top of a tower just being an
aesthetic and just standing on top of
his tower just praying and never coming
down so people would give him food and
so on he would sometimes pray for people
but
mostly was just there on his tower and
it was this person with no authority
whatever
that uh like all the bishops and priests
went to see to make sure that they're
like their documents was okay so
this person like the hidden part of the
church who has no explicit authority
would be that from which the the
periphery can extend that from which the
active uh priests and bishops
could could uh that makes total sense to
me yeah yeah
so and then you know in the buddhist
tradition you have
the dalai lama or something you'd be
like
the symbol of tibetan buddhism and
everybody would revere him
but but actually that the guy in the
forest you know uh that yeah
crazy man in the forest would be the guy
who's
really holding the the inner um thing
yeah
yeah yeah and another really cool
instantiation of this is
i heard this uh very recently but during
let's see medieval times it would happen
that in a cathedral
so you have the bishop in his cathedral
and he has explicit power and he's
representing the church and he's
supposed to sort of expand the church
uh you would often have like a let's say
a very pious person living as a
um as a an hermit
in like in the sale somewhere in the
cathedral
would it would be like let's say just
the if you're pious woman who was
praying that was really like all day
and the bishop would go to see her like
to talk to her all the time when he's
trying to make his decisions because
because she has like she's close to the
center she's close to the art of christ
like john
so she like she's the part of
christianity that doesn't change like
the very
very pious part that is invisible and
close to the heart
that's the part that the church that
can't change but right
the the hour the explicit like the part
that uh will die
the the bishop is the one who has to
talk to the center so that we can then
carry it outward
yeah that makes me think a little bit
uh about you know you know we're having
these kind of conversations
in public in a sense but on youtube
and uh and being kind of public
but the people i know who are the most
spiritual are probably
they're not they're not me they're
they're very humble people that nobody
would ever talk to or me
you know or that don't even have no
interest in
in uh maybe i'm maybe i'm i'm
uh maybe i'm putting down this kind of
activity i don't need
to do that either but but just i i've
noticed that
i've noticed the people who are much
more you know
advanced spiritually than me are are not
um
are not out there in the public yeah
they have to have to be on
in some level um in the private but
they're probably
doing more you know for the world
or as much i i don't know maybe i'm i'm
being too judgmental here and how i'm
saying it but
perhaps somebody praying in in in a
retreat
uh is has as much effect as a social
as somebody out there in in the middle
of the politics
doing stuff yeah yeah i think
yeah within christianity i think
different traditions will
tend to emphasize one branch let's say
the active or the contemplative
and i think if you go back to the first
apostles i think it's a mistake to see
it
in terms of a like of one era key where
you could fit
all of the apostles or like all of the
different vocations i think rather it's
supposed to be really a
a body where you have different people
have different kinds of authority
and as long as they they work together
in a body then
you have then it's actually the best
thing for everyone so
in in what i mentioned earlier there's a
sense in which
john is higher because he is closer to
the art of christ because he's
contemplative because he has the part of
christianity that will never die
but on the other end like he
he couldn't even survive without peter
who is expanding the church
who is like making sure that like the
tradition doesn't actually die that
christianity doesn't get wiped out right
for instance and you can see this at a
okay so you can see this in in what
occurred within orthodox christianity
and catholic
and the catholic church so the two
churches got split
because partly of theological
differences because of linguistic but
but also because of the the because of
islam that just sort of
cut the two parts of the christian
empire uh and
the orthodox church has been putting
much more emphasis on monasticism on
john
you can really see them as john they
don't they don't change they don't
evangelize much
uh but they they have like a mystical
quality to them don't they
as well perhaps they work more with with
with symbols and they're less
propositional
and their theology is great like it
hasn't changed forever but
it's really great and you that's why you
see people like time coming from the
tradition and can like say things that
are extremely impressive
uh that are that are true and so
you can see this from the other
expedition and they put monasticism at a
very high level
all of their their bishops or monks
right uh and like basically the best
thing in terms of vocation you can do in
the
lectures is to be to be a monk like the
only reason not to be a monk is because
you can't handle it
uh if you can you should definitely be
alone whereas in the
so being married and having children is
a lesser sort of
uh yeah it's good it's good but it's not
as good it's not as good yeah sure
and within the catholic church then we
put more emphasis on peter on being
like a priest um so it's and yeah
there's always a tension there because i
was talking to this about my spiritual
director and was
explaining to me that well i mean
ultimately you have to do what
like god is calling you to individually
like if you're called to marriage it's
the best thing you can do
but like at the level of the
organization then the most important
thing is to be is to be a priest
so there's this tension there but
there's still this idea that if you're
like if you can be a priest it's sort of
what you should do and assuming that in
the orthodox church if you can be
uh it's what you should do you have the
the active versus the contemplative in
those two traditions
uh and what and what has happened
historically is
the orthodox church was almost wiped out
yeah
uh by by islam and then by communism
recently
but it has re-emerged both times in in
part i think because
like the west rome peter has been able
to
like stop those uh
those agents like stop uh the spirit of
islam and also it didn't get it didn't
get destroyed in the same way that
uh it remained yeah because it was
probably more active
you know and politically in that kind of
thing yeah
so so the the the inner like the pious
people
that are the ideal part of the church
doesn't get
simply wiped out in part because of the
active part of the church and the church
can also extend this
so like i don't think it would be fair
to say that
one of the two hierarchies is better
like you need you need mounts and you
need priests
uh and you need married people that's
why i was stopping myself when i was
saying oh maybe i'm you know i
i'm saying all the person in the forest
is better than the
the person who's right on the front
lines it's not that it's not better it's
it's it's more like who is fulfilling
their their archetype or or who is
you know who is who is who is more
faithful to their essence
yeah who's playing their part in the in
in the body like in the community
it's i think it would be like a
community right yeah i think it would be
like asking
was was it better when christ was
like praying in the garden of gethsemane
before being uh
betrayed or when he was crucified like
was it better when he was
uh contemplative uh playing to his
father like
like john or was it better when he was
on the cross active being persecuted
there's no there's no better right yeah
that's right yeah i see what you do
yeah you made me think something i want
to like ask you about is uh
i was listening to jordan peterson came
back again and then yeah
the other day and on his uh daughter's
podcast
um and he just went through this
incredible
job experience you know uh losing
everything just losing his sanity losing
just
just that going through complete hell um
and uh and then kind of he now is kind
of coming out of it again
on some level and uh um
when you were talking about community i
was that was what's missing from his
whole philosophy which is about the
sovereign individual and the logos
and that kind of thing is this
communitas it's like it's a thing that's
missing from this for i i love
jordan peterson i think he's a wonderful
guy and uh
you know i'll defend him against all
these people who attack him but
isn't isn't that what's missing from his
his his whole perspective
of things in a sense is what what he
doesn't have a
philosophy of communitas or community or
the body of christ
he talks about christ as an individual
yeah that's a good question because he
definitely talks about family as well
and yeah one of the reasons why he was
able to pull through in the last year
was because of his family i mean
obviously that's important to him the
community of the community around him
but
but uh i want somebody's philosophy to
be a buddhist or a christian just out
there on your own
you know thinking about it
yeah yeah yeah i think it goes to
a point made by by paul bernickley uh
he puts it in a good way i think he says
without individuals
nothing changes without institutions
nothing lasts if people let's say are
inspired by jordan
but if they don't go into an institution
that can foster
like that that seed then it will just
die like it won't actually last
and i don't know jordan is a very
strange role
there are i mean he's bringing a lot of
people back to the church at the same
time isn't he he's
waking people up to spirituality yeah
but but he's doing it on the outside and
i think
part of the reason for that is is
because of the death of which
like you're talking about the death of
christianity because christianity
became so impossible to people like it
became so
um let's say it just became not viable
not viable to so many people uh
their way into it is often through him
um or or their way into just a as any
kind of spiritual perspective at all
right
um was often like oh oh there's on this
whole
you know thing that i you know that
is is missing from my life because
because
you know i i just have this narrow
reductionist materialistic view of the
world
so so uh so that's the funny thing about
him is that
i i feel like his philosophy is flawed
on some level but i also feel that that
he's doing a wonderful heroic thing yeah
and ironically i think maybe the best
way for him
to help bring back
communities is to not talk about it
directly like
because i think it's the same thing as
going on with him bringing people back
to
to to christianity because he he doesn't
identify himself as a christian like he
never
says it and by remaining
exclusively in the secular world he
can help secular people see the secular
aspects of christianity and that's
enough for people to sort of
go over the bridge themselves and yeah i
think it's the same thing for
communities
it never explicitly talks about building
communities it only talks about it in
individual terms that modern individual
people are comfortable with
so like the idea of using let's see
christian ideas
to help yourself individually and then
maybe help
your family and those around you like
it's like it's convincing
emotionally to modern people and i think
naturally from that point
perhaps perhaps that that's christianity
christianity hasn't been convincing to
people
um uh emotionally um
for a lot of reasons you know again this
is not a chris criticism of christianity
but
but it certainly wasn't convincing to me
as a young person and i think it
yeah it's not convincing to a lot of
people and so uh
yeah and jordan made it convincing by
remaining within the secular arena
and i think he can make ironically he
can make
communities attractive to people without
talking about communities directly
by just like talking about the
advantages of traditions
within uh individu yeah within purely
individualistic terms
perhaps but but i also wonder if there's
a there's just something
this idea of the logos being the
individuals the sovereign individual
is that i mean that doesn't work
with buddhist philosophy i don't know if
it works with christian philosophy the
the sovereign individual is the goal um
it doesn't it it doesn't you end up
alone you end up to be the isolated
cartesian
individual you know somehow
yeah i haven't thought through this very
very
very deeply so i'm just
and i'm wondering i mean maybe that's
the reason why he's suffering so much or
he has been suffering so much
is is he hasn't found his his his
community
on some level whatever that might be i'm
not saying it would be
i'm not saying what it would be but but
yeah i'm just posing that as a question
because yeah
you don't want to be judgmental yeah
that's it
uh i doubt that that's the reason why
he's suffering from what i heard about
his story and
also like the depression before that and
like all of the problems in his family
it seems like
all the problems that he's had have come
mostly from
kind of physiological that's what he
says yeah but i don't buy that like
see i don't buy this just the
physiological thing
you know i don't think you can explain
things in that way i think that's a
narrow way to explain things
yes it's all true i'm not saying any of
that stuff is not true
but then what's beneath that
interesting um um you know what's
beneath that is
you know all kinds of things right going
on so so i i
i wouldn't say that it's just okay he
took a drug and
i think there must be something deeper
going on there
at least that's how i see it because i
don't see
that there's a separation between the
physiological and the spiritual
and and all the all those things
yeah because he has really brought
people together as
he has helped lots of families uh
certainly
yeah he's been very helpful like to tons
of people no kidding he's
not i think he even i think he even i
think he even opened up
an entire conversation and
culture that that was like you know
didn't didn't even exist before perhaps
that's why we're talking now
yeah i think he's hugely important on
someone um
yeah so it's yeah it's possible that
yeah he's a strange figure like he has
put he has
got so many people back to church
without himself being christian he has
gotten
so many people back in their communities
without even talking really about
communities either
and okay yes we're i think i should go
probably soon
sure one last thing i'd be curious is
you know we talked we've been talking
about communities and i knew from the
the christian context i can
i can try to find a good church there
are still some of them in north america
you may have to look for a bit but you
can find something um i know that you're
living in france right now how is it to
find like buddhist communities
well there's all kinds of them in france
i mean i wouldn't recommend any of them
necessarily
[Music]
but but there's all kinds of buddhist
communities i think france has the most
buddhist communities of any country or
something
they're interesting which is which is
kind of interesting um since
it's a catholic country right yeah um
[Music]
uh so yeah i i don't
i i think it's really uh for me it's a
question of uh
okay um
it's a very intimate thing right it's
you know you know finding a teacher and
a community and it's very
it's a very intimate and personal thing
so so so so i wouldn't i wouldn't
i wouldn't recommend any anybody
becoming buddhist or anything like that
i
i wouldn't buddhism i wouldn't say go
become a buddhist i
i wouldn't do i i i i would say go
become a christian or
go become something else i don't know if
i would say that either but
um but uh but uh
so you have to find that i think you
have to find a good
uh you have to go you know traditionally
buddhism is buddha dharma
sangha so buddha is is you know you
would be like you you need to find a
teacher you need to find a community and
and you need to study a lot
and it has to be the one community that
you love
and that works with your particular uh
yeah
oh yes so you see that your particular
nature so so there's there's
there's take your pick there's all kinds
of all kinds of things and some of them
are more
authentic and um and grounded
than others i would say avoid the like
the
there's this kind of do-it-yourself
thing which
the way they teach buddhism today is
like it's meditation and mindfulness and
and
so it's about becoming mindful and just
it's such it's such a narrow perspective
it's it's so it's like you become
mindful just
so that you can become a good worker and
you know it's been co-opted by a lot of
corporate things and
it's a new age and and all that so
a lot of it is very it's very ugly um
um and uh but but but if you can find a
you know a good teacher whom you love
that's the best thing
if you can find that that's number one
if you can find a good teacher
that's number one and then if you can
find a good community that's probably
number two
yeah okay yeah i think the teacher in
buddhism the teacher comes
first which is often we don't like
teachers in the society everybody wants
to be
um because because everybody wants to be
an individual and just make up things
for themselves but i think we're making
a mistake when we don't
observe the fact that we can we can
learn from from somebody who's
who's more um
you know who has more much more
experience and
and depth than we do and there's always
somebody who has more experience than us
you know
you know we can't ever um
so i i i'm against a kind of
individualism
and i'm against the buddhism that is i'm
complaining about buddhism now here
where is it supposed to be perhaps but
i'm against the kind of buddhism that is
that is
is is just uh a self-help
or or a thing or a series of of
esoteric techniques that people like to
escape from their own
identity and culture and yeah but i
think yeah there's an authentic there's
a there's
you just have to you just have to
um you have to do a lot of work and
research and
and and to find the right one and i
wouldn't want to say what that is
yeah yes yes it's a sign of our
strange times where we okay so we know
that we need communities
but because so many of our communities
are broken down we can't just go like
when they
willingly take any community we have to
so individually work
to find communities where you'll find
good individuals as well
in in terms of finding a good teacher
within a christian context
finding a pair a parish with a good
priest yeah and
no because the priest is good then you
will find a good community there as well
at the same time but
because we live in a strange world where
it's so fragmented you know you may have
to look
for a while until you find something
that works
actually well before you find a good
community yeah
i think a lot of people are going to the
orthodox tradition too because
yeah finding something fresh there yeah
these days because perhaps maybe that's
as you say if the orthodox tradition
is a more clinical tradition you know
which has more
um in a way i think that's what we need
today is is more of that
rather than than there's too much of
this political noise and
you know and dogma and ideology
um and we're too easily fooled by that
we need to go away from the world
in some level right we need to yeah yeah
we need to go back to the center
we go back to john to the part that is
yeah we need to go back to john
exactly yeah yeah that's right i would
agree with that yeah
cool all right so on that note uh i'll
stop the recording so
thanks uh andrew it was really cool so
much it was a big pleasure for me yeah